CIO Files of John L. Lewis, Pt. II: CIO General Files on Microfilm 5831 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
CIO Files of John L. Lewis, Pt. II: CIO General Files on Microfilm
1922-1962
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Lewis, John L. (John Llewellyn), 1880-1969
Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.)
5831 mf
2.22 cubic feet
20 microfilm reels
Articles, reports, pamphlets, correspondence, manuscripts, microfilm.
This collection documents the origins and early history of the CIO as well as the dynamics of working-class militancy in the era of the Great Depression. The collection also provides a substantial amount of information concerning workers and trade unionism before the creation of the CIO and also after the UMWA's separation from the CIO in 1942.
3337595
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, April 21, 2014
Biographical / Historical
From its founding in 1935 until 1942, the history of the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) was inseparable from that of John L. Lewis and the United Mine Workers of America (UMWA). Lewis created the CIO as an organization, and he used the manpower and treasury of the UMWA to keep the CIO alive. The early history of the CIO was also greatly influenced by the relationship between Lewis and Franklin D. Roosevelt. In 1935, the CIO devoted the bulk of its assets and energies to Roosevelt's re-election campaign. Roosevelt's victory in 1936 set the stage for the CIO's triumph over General Motors and United States Steel in early 1937. As the Lewis-Roosevelt relationship began to cool in 1937, the CIO lost ground to the AFL, Lewis resigned as president of the CIO in 1940, and the UMWA left the CIO two years after that.
Scope and Contents
The CIO general files (1935-1955) include correspondence, CIO personnel files, committee files, financial records, and convention files. Subjects covered include organizing drives in rubber, auto, steel, electronics, timbering and shipbuilding industries; the rift between the AFL and CIO; the development of the CIO national staff; national politics; communism in the CIO; competition between the CIO and the UMWA in organizing industrial unions; impact of Taft-Hartley Act; and AFL-CIO merger negotiations.
The United Mine Workers of America files regarding loans and financial aid to CIO unions and industrial unions (1922-1955) document a number of loans made by the UMWA to industrial unions and to the CIO itself. Of special interest are the files on the CIO and the Teamsters loans.
The CIO Field Office files (1937-1942) contain records both from the CIO field offices and from Industrial Union Councils. These files document the CIO's jurisdictional and factional disputes, political activities and organizing drives.
The AFL general files (1929-1955) comprise John L. Lewis's correspondence both with and about AFL officials. The material documents the rise of industrial unionism in the 1930s and the formation of the CIO, and it provides information on the UMWA's reaffiliation and second disaffiliation from the AFL in 1946 and 1947, respectively. Files for later years provide valuable material on the AFL-CIO merger in 1955.
United Steelworkers of America (1949-1962) is a continuation of the Steelworkers files in part I. For the most part the series is a newsclipping file; however, there are records detailing the UMWA strike fund assistance to the steelworkers, and there is some material relative to the proposed federation of the UMWA, the steelworkers union, and the Teamsters in the 1950s.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5830 mf: The CIO Files of John L. Lewis, Pt. I: Correspondence with CIO Unions.
Labor unions -- United States -- Officials and employees; Labor unions -- United States -- Political activity; Labor unions and communism -- United States; Labor leaders; Labor unions -- United States -- Consolidation; Lewis, John L. (John Llewellyn), 1880-1969; Boehm, Randolph,; American Federation of Labor; Congress of Industrial Organizations (U.S.); International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America; United Mine Workers of America; United Steelworkers of America
3337595
- Minutes, Correspondence, and General Files, 1935-1937 (Reel 1)
  - CIO-Meetings, 1935; 1 (Reel 1)
    Scope and Contents
    34 pp.: Minutes of meetings; reports of director; response to AFL allegations regarding formation of CIO; organization of steelworkers, radio workers, and auto workers; Charles P. Howard; John Brophy; William Green.
  - CIO-AFL Controversy-Releases and Correspondence, 1935; 2 (Reel 1)
    69 pp.: Industrial unionism; 1935 AFL convention; publications; William Green; John Brophy; Philip Murray; Thomas Kennedy; Charles P. Howard; Harvey C. Fremming; Thomas F. McMahon; Max Zaritsky.
  - CIO-John Brophy, Director, 1935; 3 (Reel 1)
    50 pp.: UMWA support for CIO; organization plans; Brotherhood of Utility Employees of America conflict with IBEW; IUMMSW and UMWA unity negotiations; minutes of meetings of UAW Conference of FLUs; UAW wage scales; John Brophy; Joseph Mayo; Nicholas Fontecchio; Ellis Searles; A.D. Lewis; John Soltis.
  - CIO-AFL Controversy--Releases and Correspondence, 1936; 4 (Reel 1)
    155 pp.: 1936 AFL convention; AFL reorganization and executive council dominance of crafts unions; UMWA trial of AFL president William Green@CIO organization of steelworkers and radio workers; jurisdictional disputes of CIO affiliates with AFL crafts unions; growth in membership of CIO; AFL-CIO unity negotiations; AFL suspension of CIO affiliates; Alabama State Federation of Labor support for CIO; Wisconsin State Federation of Labor proposal for labor unity; AFL Metal Trades Department charges against CIO; John Brophy; William Green; Charles P. Howard; Van A. Bittner; Vincent Sweeney; Max Zaritsky; David Dubinsky; Sidney Hillman; George M. Harrison; William Mitch; Henry Ohl; John P. Frey; G.M. Bugniazel; Joseph N. Weber; Frank Morrison.
  - CIO--General, 1936; 5 (Reel 1)
    158 pp.: Growth in membership of CIO@CIO organization of auto workers, rubber workers, steelworkers, electrical and radio workers, shipbuilding workers, shoe workers, and woodworkers; publications; conflict with AFL@CIO and SWOC financial matters; social security and legislative programs; Senator Robert M. La Follette committee identification security and legislative programs; Senator Robert M. La Follette committee identification of spies employed by the National Corporation Service; statements of church groups supporting union organization@CIO organization in the Pacific Northwest; UMWA organizers; AFL Metal Trades Department charges against CIO; UMWA support for SWOC; Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel, and Tin Workers agreement with CIO; reports of the director; John Brophy; William Green; John O'Leary; John Zimmerman; William Dalrymple; Abe Vales; John P. Frey; Glen W. McCabe.
  - CIO--Meetings, 1936; 6 (Reel 1)
    45 pp.: AFL-CIO controversy; SWOC; unity negotiations; reports of the director; minutes of meetings. Charles P. Howard; Sidney Hillman; David Dubinsky; Thomas F. McMahon; Harvey C. Fremming; Max Zaritsky; William Green; John Brophy.
  - CIO--Personnel, Powers Hapgood, International Representative, 1935-1936; 7 (Reel 1)
    17 pp.: UMWA organizers; allegations of Socialist influence; Powers Hapgood; James Nelson.
  - CIO--Office Personnel, Hazelle M. Camp, 1936; 8 (Reel 1)
    3 pp.: Kathryn Lewis; Hazelle M. Camp.
  - Action of UMWA Executive Council on Case of William Green, 1936; 9 (Reel 1)
    33 pp; UMWA trial of AFL president William Green; AFL- CIO controversy; William Green; Philip Murray; Thomas Kennedy; Walter Smethurst; John Ghizzoni; John O'Leary; Ora E. Gasaway; John J. Mates; Henry Allai.
  - CIO--General, 1937; 10 (Reel 1)
    294 pp.: Oil Workers International Union contract negotiations; local industrial union charters and growth in CIO membership; NLRB decisions; UMWA organizers@United Lumber Workers contract negotiations; US Department of Justice prosecution of SWOC members and S.S. Algic crewmen; 1937 CIO conference; plans for CIO convention@United Retail Employees of America request for loan and organizers; UMWA District 50 organizers@CIO financial matters@United Textile Workers of America; statistics by state and union on growth in local industrial unions; Speakers Bureau activities; UCAPAWA locals by state and occupation; jurisdictional disputes@CIO organization plans regarding chartering of unions and jurisdiction by occupation; E.C. Conarty; Mary Evelyn Bendelari; Kathryn Lewis; John Ghizzoni; Lee Pressman; J. Raymond Bell; Philip Murray; Walter Smethurst; James Starr; John Brophy.
  - CIO--Office General, 1937; 11 (Reel 1)
    239 pp.: Founding of United Furniture Workers of America; number of field representatives allotted to national and international unions; NLRB policy regarding industrial unionism; weekly analyses of U.S. economic conditions by industry; lists of CIO regional directors and field representatives by state; lists of presidents and secretaries of CIO national and international unions; negotiations with UOPWA CIO office unit; publications; draft constitution and rules for local industrial unions; loans to United Retail Employees of America and Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America; lists of local industrial unions@CIO rental of office space@CIO organizational structure and officers; Illinois state unemployment compensation legislation; UMWA and CIO cooperation; Labor's Non-Partisan League; proposal of US Constitution amendment to reform the judiciary; John Brophy; Lee Pressman; Ralph Hetzel; John Bell; Len De Caux; Walter Smethurst; Ora E. Gasaway; Kathryn Lewis; Mary Evelyn Bendelari; David J. McDonald; A.D. Lewis; Maurice Sugar; Eli L. Oliver.
- Minutes, Correspondence, and General Files, 1937-1938 (Reel 2)
  - CIO-AFL Controversy--Releases and Correspondence, 1937; 1 (Reel 2)
    73 pp.: Founding of United Furniture Workers of America; results of AFL-CIO unity negotiations; AFL jurisdictional disputes with CIO affiliates; AFL executive council internal politics; UMWA support for UAW contract negotiations with General Motors Corporation; 1937 CIO conference; legislative programs; NLRB decisions; Philip Murray; Frank Morrison; Harvey C. Fremming; Charles P. Howard; Sidney Hillman; David Dubinsky; Homer Martin; James B. Carey; Richard Frankensteen; Sherman H. Dalrymple; Donald Henderson; Van A. Bittner.
  - CIO--Miscellaneous Releases., 1937; 2 (Reel 2)
    109 pp; WPA workers and CIO unemployment programs; legislative programs; Social Security Act provisions; union organization; founding of United Furniture Workers of America@CIO regional directors; NLRB elections; American Radio Telegraphists contract negotiations; founding of TWOC; anti-union violence against UAW officers in Anderson, IN; publications; John Brophy; Walter Smethurst; Richard Francis; Lee Pressman; George L. Berry; Francis Gorman; Frances Perkins; Edward Hall.
  - CIO--Meeting., 1937; 3 (Reel 2)
    March 9, 1937. 12 pp; Report of director; national and international union requests for CIO affiliation; regional and state organization; financial matters.
  - Agreement between CIO and United Textile Workers of America., 1937; 4 (Reel 2)
    March 1937. 3 pp.: Founding of TWOC; Francis Gorman; Charles P. Howard; Sidney Hillman.
  - CIO Convention--Atlantic City, NJ (Part 1)., 1937; 5 (Reel 2)
    October 1937. 316 pp.: Informal minutes of CIO conference, October 11-15, 1937; SWOC report; report of director; NMU report; American Newspaper Guild report; special Southern report@United Packing House Workers Council report; TWOC report; IWA report@CIO Maritime Committee report; UERMWA report; Transport Workers Union of America report; ACA report; Shoe Workers Organizing Committee report; AFL-CIO unity negotiations; UMWA District 50 report; safety and health; National Leather Workers Association report; ILWU report; Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America report; legislative programs; NLRB decisions@United Retail Employees of America report; Pacific Northwest jurisdictional disputes with AFL; political activities; Toy and Novelty Workers Organizing Committee report; Aluminum Workers of America report; UCAPAWA report@United Federal Workers of America report; IUMMSW report; State, County, and Municipal Workers of America report; UAW report; UOPWA report; URW report; Federation of Architects, Engineers, Chemists, and Technicians report; Philip Murray; John Brophy; Joseph Curran; Heywood Broun; Jonathan Eddy; Victor Pasche; Walter Smethurst; Sidney Hillman; Harold Pritchett; Mervyn Rathborne; James B. Carey; Michael Quill; Powers Hapgood; Lee Pressman; David Dubinsky; Homer Martin; James Nelson; Abram Flaxer; Daniel Boyle; Harry Bridges; John Green; C.W. Deal; Louis Leonard; Alexander Ravitch; Paul W. Fuller; N.A. Zonarich; Donald Henderson; Reid Robinson; Lewis Merrill; Sherman H. Dalrymple; Lewis Alan Berne; Samuel Wolchok.
  - CIO Convention--Atlantic City, NJ (Part 2)., 1937; 6 (Reel 2)
    October 1937. 161 pp.: Committee reports to CIO conference; Special Committee on Finance report; report of director; growth in membership of CIO; NLRB election statistics; resolutions of CIO conference; speeches to CIO conference; AFL-CIO unity negotiations; South Chicago Memorial Day massacre; Walter Smethurst; John Brophy; Philip Murray; Van A. Bittner.
  - CIO--Auxiliary Organization, Edwardsville, IL., 1937; 7 (Reel 2)
    3 pp.: Local CIO support group.
  - CIO--Speakers Bureau, 1937; 8 (Reel 2)
    23 pp.: UOPWA CIO office unit protest against work of Mary Evelyn Bendelari in Charter department; Speakers Bureau Labor Day activities; publicity; Kathryn Lewis; Mary Evelyn Bendelari; Len De Caux.
  - CIO--Office Personnel, Bell, J. Raymond., 1937; 9 (Reel 2)
    4 pp.: Appointment as CIO comptroller; appointment of Richard Francis to SWOC payroll; John Brophy; J. Raymond Bell; David J. McDonald; Kathryn Lewis.
  - CIO--Personnel, Bendelari, Mary Evelyn., 1937; 10 (Reel 2)
    4 pp.: Appointment as chief of the Division of Chartered Organizations and Speakers Bureau; Walter Smethurst; Kathryn Lewis; Mary Evelyn Bendelari.
  - CIO--Personnel, Dernoncourt, Joseph., 1937; 11 (Reel 2)
    4 pp.: Criticism of CIO and UMWA organizer Dernoncourt; boycott of General Motors Corporation products during UAW strike.
  - CIO--Personnel, DuBois, Marian (later Mrs. Ralph Hetzel)., 1937; 12 (Reel 2)
    2 pp.: Letter of recommendation; Edwin S. Smith.
  - CIO--Personnel, Haywood, Allan S., 1937; 13 (Reel 2)
    3 pp.: Congratulations on General Motors Corporation contract negotiations; Allan S. Haywood.
  - CIO--Office Personnel, Hetzel, Ralph., 1937; 14 (Reel 2)
    2 pp.: Appointment as secretary to CIO chairman; Walter Smethurst.
  - CIO--Personnel, Kovner, Joseph (Legal Dept.)., 1937; 15 (Reel 2)
    6 pp.: Appointment as assistant to Lee Pressman; background and experience; Lee Pressman; John Brophy; Joseph Kovner.
  - CIO--Personnel, Pressman, Lee (Legal Dept)., 1937; 16 (Reel 2)
    3 pp.: Appointment as CIO Counsel; Philip Murray; David J. McDonald; John Brophy.
  - CIO--Personnel, Smethurst, Walter., 1937; 17 (Reel 2)
    3 pp.: Plans for birthday celebration.
  - CIO--Personnel, Suttle, John H., 1937; 18 (Reel 2)
    4 pp.: Appointment as CIO organizers; Virginia E. Jenckes; John Brophy.
  - Request from Various Groups of Workers for Organization under CIO., 1937; 19 (Reel 2)
    28 pp.: Proposed organization of domestic and farm workers.
  - CIO--General., 1938; 20 (Reel 2)
    175 pp.: Office space for Labor's Non-Partisan League; AFL competition with CIO; NLRB elections@CIO organizers; UMWA organizers@CIO regional directors; UMWA executive council matters; organization in New York, Illinois, Utah, Wyoming, Montana, Nebraska, Tennessee, Pennsylvania, North Carolina, Colorado, Kansas, and Michigan; factionalism and internal politics; organization of black workers and Communist activities among Omaha, Nebraska, packing house workers; Communist activities among Duluth, Minnesota, steelworkers; legislative programs; Tennessee Valley Authority electrification competition with coal industry; growth in membership of CIO; Communist activities, factionalism, and internal politics among Detroit, Michigan, auto workers; organization of WPA workers; A.D. Lewis; Walter Smethurst; David W. Davis; James Morgan; Thomas Kennedy; John Brophy; Ben Williams; Harmon R. Ballard; Ora E. Gasaway; Tom Jones; Joseph Angelo; Kathryn Lewis; Philip Murray; Walter N. Polakov; David H. Watkins; Tom White.
- Minutes, Correspondence, and General Files, 1938 (Reel 3)
  - CIO--Office General., 1938; 1 (Reel 3)
    165 pp.: CIO organizers; personnel matters; lists of CIO personnel and comparison of regional office expenses; Jersey City, NJ, civil rights case; publicity; financial matters of The CIO News; Dies Committee hearings; Labor Day activities; plans for CIO constitutional convention; NLRB decisions; CIO Legal Department bulletins; proposed amendments of Wagner Act; Walter Smethurst; J. Raymond Bell; Kathryn Lewis; Len De Caux; John Brophy; Philip Murray; A.D. Lewis; Ralph Hetzel.
  - CIO--General File., 1938; 2 (Reel 3)
    54 pp.: Agreement between CIO and UOPWA CIO office unit; contract negotiations; NLRB decision in the matter of Inland Steel Company and SWOC; growth of The CIO News and proposed mailing to UMWA membership; Joseph Kovner; Hollace Ransdell; Walter Smethurst; J. Raymond Bell; J. Warrne Madden; Edwin S. Smith; Donald Wakefield Smith; Kathryn Lewis; Len De Caux. John Brophy.
  - CIO--Meetings., 1938; 3 (Reel 3)
    9 pp.: CIO staff meetings; Labor's Non-Partisan League; legislative programs; Eli L. Oliver.
  - CIO Conference, 1938; 4 (Reel 3)
    Washington, DC. April 12-13, 1938. 121 pp.: Digest of proceedings; report of director; report of comptroller; report on The CIO News and publicity; report of legal department; report on unemployment activities; Workers Alliance of America; reports of affiliated organizations; legislative programs; growth in membership of CIO; John Brophy; J. Raymond Bell; Len De Caux; Lee Pressman; Ralph Hetzel; Richard Frankensteen; Joseph Curran; Charles P. Howard; Sidney Hillman; Homer Martin; Julius Hochman; Samuel J. Hogan; Jacob F. Potofsky; James Nelson; Morris Muster; Allan S. Haywood; Mervyn Rathborne; Lewis Alan Berne; Sherman H. Dalrymple; Samuel Wolchok; Lewis Merrill; Emil Rieve; Philip Murray; Abram Flaxer; Albert Stonkus; James B. Carey; David Lasser; Samuel Levin; Donald Henderson; Harvey C. Fremming; James Lawson; Paul W. Fuller; Reid Robinson; Jacob Baker; Michael Quill; Powers Hapgood; Eli L. Oliver; John Green; N.A. Zonarich; E.C. Conarty; Harold Pritchett.
  - CIO First Constitutional Convention, 1938; 5 (Reel 3)
    Pittsburgh, PA. November 14-18, 1938 [October 28-November 19, 1938]. 183 pp.: Greetings to convention; constitution; report of chairman; UMWA report; lists of delegates and committee memberships; AFL-CIO unity negotiations; convention resolutions; plans for convention; Franklin D. Roosevelt; John Brophy; John Owens; Frank Miley; Lee Pressman; David J. McDonald.
  - CIO--Audits and Accounting., 1938; 6 (Reel 3)
    70 pp.: Financial matters; per capita payment by affiliates; CIO payroll expenses; Leo F. Tearney; Len De Caux; Kathryn Lewis; J. Raymond Bell; Walter Smethurst; Ralph Hetzel.
  - CIO--Committee on Education., 1938; 7 (Reel 3)
    14 pp.: Proposed CIO adult education program; Ralph Hetzel; Ralph E. Turner.
  - CIO--Housing Committee., 1938; 8 (Reel 3)
    10 pp.: Cooperation with US Housing Authority; low-rent housing projects; Anthony Wayne Smith; Michael Quill; Bertram M. Gross; Ellis Searles; Kathryn Lewis.
  - CIO--Legislative Committee., 1938; 9 (Reel 3)
    7 pp.: Legislative programs; Labor's Non-Partisan League; Sidney Hillman; Eli L. Oliver.
  - CIO--Personnel--Office., 1938; 10 (Reel 3)
    13 pp.: CIO relations with UOPWA CIO office unit; appointment of Hildegarde Gray; Walter Smethurst; Ralph Hetzel; A.D. Lewis; J. Roymond Bell; Frank Sobers.
  - CIO--Research Department., 1938; 11 (Reel 3)
    138 pp.: Domestic and world economic conditions; labor, economic conditions, and political relations in Maryland, Pennsylvania, West Virginia, Ohio, Indiana, Illinois, Wisconsin, Minnesota, North Dakota, South Dakota, and Montana; U.S. urban economic conditions; industrial survey of Florida, South Carolina, North Carolina, Alabama, Tennessee, Georgia, Mississippi, and Louisiana; survey of distilled liquors industry; copper industry; average hourly earnings for major industries; memorandum on the movie industry; sugar productions; AFL-CIO unity negotiations; innovative wage and hour policy and labor-management relations of the Hormel Packing Company; CIO public relations; legislative programs; James Gillan.
  - CIO--Social Security Committee., 1938; 12 (Reel 3)
    8 pp.: Reports of Social Security Committee; Charles P. Howard; Joseph Kovner.
  - CIO--Unemployment Committee., 1938; 13 (Reel 3)
    91 pp.: WPA; legislative programs; wage and hour legislation; Fair Labor Standards Act of 1938; organizations of unemployed and WPA workers; federal relief programs; joint meeting with regional directors; Workers Alliance of America. Ralph Hetzel; Anthony Wayne Smith; Kathryn Lewis.
  - The Story of the CIO., 1938; 14 (Reel 3)
    28 pp.: AFL-CIO unity negotiations; founding of CIO; analysis of affiliates; James Gillan.
- Minutes, Correspondence, and General Files, 1939-1941 (Reel 4)
  - CIO--Office General., 1939; 1 (Reel 4)
    149 pp.: U.S. monetary policy; Temporary National Economic Committee hearings on technology changes and employment; transfer of John Brophy and Walter Smethurst from UMWA to CIO payrolls; Consumers Power Corporation strikes in Michigan; CIO organizers; WPA projects in Montana; Southern Coal Operators Association; Interstate Commerce Commission; crafts unionism; AFL competition with CIO; plans for 1939 CIO convention; Harry Bridges Defense Committee; reactions of US congressmen to attack of John L. Lewis on US vice president John Nance Garner; PWOC; CIO relations with UOPWA CIO office unit; resignation of Harvey C. Fremming as Social Security committee chairman; WPA and federal relief programs in connection with UMWA work stoppage in West Virginia, Kentucky, and Alabama; support for UMWA contract negotiations; CIO unemployment program; CIO office space lease arrangements; issuance of new CIO charters following reorganization; AFL-CIO unity negotiations; suspension of CIO affiliates from the Trades and Labor Congress of Canada; proposed amendment of Wagner Act; lists of CIO regional and subregional directors, officers of national and international affiliates, and executive board members; Ralph Hetzel; Lee Pressman; Walter Smethurst; Rinaldo Cappellini; James Gillan; J. Raymond Bell; Kathryn Lewis; John Brophy; Len De Caux; Ramsey Wilson; Ora E. Gasaway; A.D. Lewis; Joseph Kovner; Anthony Wayne Smith; Frank Hefferly; D.W. Morrison; R.J. Tallon; Walter N. Polakov; Philip Murray.
  - CIO--General., 1939; 2 (Reel 4)
    21 pp.: AFL-CIO unity negotiations; founding of United Construction Workers Organizing Committee; UMWA cooperation; proposed mine foremen and assistants union; proposed replacement of The CIO News; A.D. Lewis; John Owens; James Mark; Van A. Bittner; Ellis Searles; Frank Miley.